Early in the 20th year of Yuankang
元康二十年の初め
Zu Kun broke through Beiyu Pass
祖坤が北域の関所を大破した
Afterward
その後
With the Wuzhao at the Hanshui line
ウーウと瀚水で一緒に
In a long stalemate
長年にわたる対立
In June of the 23rd year of Yuankang
元康二十三年六月
Zu Kun again petitioned for the northern expedition
祖坤は再び表を上げて北伐を請願した
The emperor did not approve
天子は応じなかった
Ordered him to withdraw and return to court
命じて兵を引き返させ朝廷に戻らせた
Rise, rise
起きろ起きろ
Yet the northern people knelt to keep the royal army
しかし北国の民は王の軍を迎えて跪いた
Volunteer armies also responded
義軍も次々と応じた
That September
あの年の九月
Zu Kun captured Zhongzhou
祖坤は中州を攻め取る
Causing great shock in the court
朝廷に大きな動揺をもたらした
Defeat would harm the state
敗れると国を誤る
Your Majesty
陛下
This war really cannot continue
この戦いは本当にもう続けられない
The court issued eight imperial edicts
朝廷は続けて八つの聖旨を発布した
Ordering Zu Kun not to advance further
命祖坤はこれ以上進むことができない
While cutting off his supplies
同時にその食糧と飼料を断つ
Secretly ordered Chen Ying and others to withdraw
命令陳応らの軍を撤退させる
October
10月
Chen Ying
チェンイン
Crossed south over Tianhe
天の川を南に渡る
Occupied the ferry behind Zu Kun
祖坤の背後の渡し場を占拠する
Zu Kun knew
祖坤は自分を知っている
To press on
勢いをそのままにする
To take Yong'an was hopeless
永安を攻略するのはもう望みがない
Years of war's accumulated ills
長年の戦争による弊害
Coupled with inner frustration
心の中に憤りが加わった
Illness struck like a mountain
病は山のように降りかかる
General
将軍
Soon
まもなく
Soon passed away at
まもなく亡くなった
Beiyu Pass
北域の関所
General
将軍
My father told me
父が私に言った
He lived in Yong'an as a youth
彼は子供の頃永安で生活していた
Always thought Yong'an wasn't special
どうも永安には特に良いところがないように感じる
Those scholars' Ba willow trees
あの書生たちの口に上る灞上の柳
Yong'an flowers
永安花
Were just ordinary
まあそんなものだ
All these years
こんなに長い年月
I never thought my father
私は父をそう思ったことが一度もありません
Cared much about that hometown
あの故郷をどれほど大切に思っていたか
Doing all this
これを全部やる
Was just for advancement
ただ将来のためだけに
For reputation
名声のために
For those tens of thousands of
部下のあの数万枚のために
Hungry mouths under him
お腹を空かせて待っている口
But this time
しかし今回は
Taking Beiyu Pass
北域を取った
I realized
私はちょうど気づいた
He actually cared so much
彼は実際にはそんなに思っている
He stood right here
彼はここに立っています
He told me
彼は私に言った
Standing this high
もうこんなに高く立っている
Why still can't see Yong'an?
どうしてまだ永安が見えないのですか
Raising my eyes, I see the sun
目を上げて日の光を見る
But not Yong'an
永安を見えず
Maybe when people get old
年を取ったからかもしれません
They always miss home
きっと故郷を懐かしく思うでしょう
Your Highness in the palace, honored and precious
殿下は皇城で金と玉のように尊ばれています
Servants like clouds
僕や召使いが雲のように多い
Pushing for the northern expedition
一力の北伐
Do you truly care about these northern lives
本当に北の連中の屑の命を問題にしてるんだな
Or to win hearts
やはり人心を引き締めるためだ
To gain leverage in the succession?
大きなポジションを争うために複数の切り札を持たせる